Archer Milton Huntington Papers
Archer Milton Huntington Papers
1919-1957
Huntington, Archer M. (Archer Milton), 1870-1955
51.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American philanthropist, poet. Correspondence; secretarial daybooks, 1922-1957; manuscripts; legal and financial papers. Organizational correspondence includes that of the Academy of American Poets, American Academy of Arts and Letters, American Geographical Society, American Museum of Natural History, American Numismatic Society, Brookgreen Gardens, California Palace of the Legion of Honor, Hispanic Society of America, Mariners' Museum, Metropolitan Museum of Art, Museum of the American Indian, National Academy of Design, National Arts Club, National Sculpture Society, New-York Historical Society, New York Zoological Society, and Yale University.
144595
Biographical History
Archer Milton Huntington (1870-1955) was an American philanthropist, art patron, scholar and poet. The son of Arabella Duval Huntington and her husband, railroad industrialist Collis P. Huntington, Archer made substantial contributions -- both scholarly and financial -- in his chosen fields, though he is particularly known for his work in Hispanic Studies. He wrote several scholarly works in the field and in 1904 founded The Hispanic Society of America in New York City, a museum and rare books library which he helped fill with an impressive collection of Hispanic paintings, decorative art, books, manuscripts, maps, prints, and photographs. At about this same time, Archer was named foreign corresponding secretary for the New-York Historical Society; he served in this capacity for several years and contributed to the funding of many of the society's publications.
His first wife, whom he married in 1895, was Helen Manchester Gates, an Englishwoman and author. For his second wife (married in 1923), sculptor Anna Hyatt Huntington, Archer founded Brookgreen Gardens in South Carolina where her works were displayed as well as those of dozens of other American sculptors. (She returned the favor, creating several Hispanic-themed works for the grounds of the Hispanic Society, including an equestrian sculpture entitled "The Cid.")
In 1936, Huntington donated an endowment which established the Chair of Poetry at the Library of Congress, now known as the Poet Laureate Consultant in Poetry to the Library of Congress; he also donated to the American Numismatic Society the funding and land for its headquarters and, later, a library. Together with Anna, he founded the Mariners' Museum in Newport News, Virginia, one of the largest and finest maritime museums in the world, and established the Archer and Anna Huntington Wild Life Forest Station in the Adirondacks of New York State.
Archer M. Huntington was awarded honorary degrees from Harvard, Yale, Columbia, Kenyon College, and the University of Madrid. Among his other philanthropic positions, he was president of the American Geographical Society and a trustee of the American Museum of Natural History, the New-York Historical Society, the Museum of the American Indian, and the Heye Foundation. When he died in December of 1955, The Modern Language Journal published a biographical sketch which included the following praise:
In his passing, Hispanic studies in the United States, Spain, and Hispanic America have lost a generous patron who was also in his own right a scholar of distinction, a poet of charm, and in everything he did a good citizen." (The Modern Language Journal, Feb 1956, p. 59)
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Archer Milton Huntington Papers contains correspondence, secretarial notes (memos, letters and daybooks), writings, legal and financial papers, and ledgers.
Correspondence (Boxes 1 through 9) has been entirely merged into the Correspondence-subject files for the Anna Hyatt Huntington Papers (see "Related Material" below). Boxes 1-9 no longer exist in this collection. Please refer to the
Anna Hyatt Huntington Papers
for a complete listing. Briefly, this material contains incoming and outgoing correspondence with both individuals and organizations. Individual correspondents include painters (Edwin Blashfield), sculptors (Herbert and Adeline Adams, Gutzon Borglum, Donald De Lue, Gleb Derujinsky, James Earle and Laura Gardin Fraser, Harriet Whitney Frishmuth, Vincent Glinsky, Malvina Hoffman, Edward McCartan, Herman Atkins MacNeil, Paul and Isabel Manship, Brenda Putnam, Alma Spreckels, Katharine Weems), writers (Maxwell Anderson, German Arciniegas, Grosvenor Atterbury, Vicente Blasco Ibáñez, Nicholas Murray Butler, Archibald Macleish). Organizations represented in the correspondence include universities (Chatham College, Clark University, Columbia University, Harvard University, Syracuse University), museums and galleries (Brookgreen Gardens, Burr Galleries, California Palace of the Legion of Honor, Columbia Museum of Art, Corcoran Gallery of Art, Fogg Art Museum, Grand Central Art Galleries, Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery, Mariner's Museum, Museum of the City of New York, ), and professional associations (American Geographical Society, American Numismatic Society, Federal Art Project, Hispanic Society of America, National Institute of Arts and Letters, New-York Historical Society).
Secretarial notes comprises memos, letters, and daybooks spanning more than thirty years. Writings contains literary gallies, poems and literary manuscripts. Properties consists of information relating to various pieces of real estate including Brookgreen and Arbutus.
Ledgers contain financial and business information; the main subdivisions are NY receipts, estate correspondence, estate documents, general correspondence, Bank of Central Hanover receipts, and payment statements. General correspondence, formerly in Volumes 45-82 of Ledgers, has been entirely merged into the Correspondence-subject files for the Anna Hyatt Huntington Papers (see "Related Material" below). Volumes 45-82 no longer exist in this collection. Please refer to the
Anna Hyatt Huntington Papers
for a complete listing.
Arrangement of the Collection
Secretarial notes (Boxes 10-17) are arranged first by type (memos, letters, then daybooks) and within that chronologically. Writings (Boxes 18-20) are arranged alphabetically by type and Properties (Boxes 21-27) alphabetically by name of the property. Legal and financial papers (Boxes 28-36) are arranged chronologically. Ledgers (Volumes 1-139) are ordered by type and within that chronologically.
Related Material
See also the following:
Anna Hyatt Huntington Papers
Arabella Huntington Papers
Collis P. Huntington Papers
Huntington Estate Papers
Separated Material
Personal correspondence of Archer Milton Huntington (Boxes 1 through 9) and General correspondence (formerly in Volumes 45-82 of Ledgers) has been entirely merged into the Correspondence-subject filesof the Anna Hyatt Huntington Papers (see "Related Material" below). Boxes 1-9 and Volumes 45-82 no longer exist in this collection. Please refer to the
Anna Hyatt Huntington Papers
for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Poetry; Art -- Sculptors; Huntington, Archer M. (Archer Milton), 1870-1955.; Academy of American Poets.; American Academy of Arts and Letters.; American Geographical Society of New York.; American Museum of Natural History.; American Numismatic Society.; Brookgreen Gardens.; California Palace of the Legion of Honor.; Federal Art Project.; Hispanic Society of America.; Mariners' Museum (Newport News, Va.); Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.); Museum of the American Indian, Heye Foundation.; National Academy of Design (U.S.); National Arts Club (New York, N.Y.); National Sculpture Society (U.S.); New-York Historical Society.; New York Zoological Society.; Animal sculptors -- United States.; Animals in art.; Art -- Collectors and collecting.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Art museums.; Art patronage.; Bronze sculpture, American.; Endowments.; Hispanists -- United States.; Monuments.; Philanthropists -- United States.; Public art.; Public sculpture.; Sculptors -- United States.; Sculpture, American.; Sculpture, American -- 20th centur.y; Sculpture gardens.; Upper class -- United States.; United States -- Social life and customs -- 20th century.; Architectural drawings (visual works); Bank statements.; Correspondence.; Philanthropists.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  This portion of the Archer Milton Huntington Papers inventory (Boxes 1 through 9) has been entirely merged into the Correspondence-subject files for the Anna Hyatt Huntington Papers (see "Related Material" above). Boxes 1-9 no longer exist in this collection.
- Secretarial notes
  - Secretarial memos, 1934-1954 (Box 10)
  - Secretarial letters, 1924-1932 (Box 11)
  - Secretarial letters, 1933-1941 (Box 12)
  - Secretarial daybooks, 1922-1935 (Box 13)
  - Secretarial daybooks, 1935-1942 (Box 14)
  - Secretarial daybooks, 1943-1946 (Box 15)
  - Secretarial daybooks, 1947-1950 (Box 16)
  - Secretarial daybooks, 1951-1957 (Box 17)
- Writings
  - Literary gallies (Box 18, 19)
  - Poems and literary manuscripts (Box 20)
- Properties
  - Arbutus (Box 21, 22)
  - Arbutus film (photographs) of (Box 23)
  - Brookgreen, Transferred to Anna Hyatt Huntington Papers, 2008.
  - New York, Stanerigg and Pleasance (Box 25)
  - Pleasance (Box 26)
  - Adirondacks, Stanerigg, Newport News, Pine Knot (Box 27)
- Legal and financial papers
  - Legal papers, 1919 - 1955 (Box 28)
  - Financial papers (Box 29-36)
- Ledgers
  - NY receipts
    - NY receipts, Apr-Jun 1946 (Volume 1)
    - NY receipts, Jun 1946-Jun 1947 (Volume 2)
    - NY receipts, Jun-Sep 1947 (Volume 3)
    - NY receipts, Jan-Jul 1948 (Volume 4)
    - NY receipts, Jul-Dec 1948 (Volume 5)
    - NY receipts, 1948-1949 (Volume 6)
    - NY receipts, Aug 1949-Mar 1950 (Volume 7)
    - NY receipts, Apr-Sep 1950 (Volume 8)
    - NY receipts, Jun 1950-Sep 1951 (Volume 9)
    - NY receipts, Jul 1951-Jan 1952 (Volume 10)
    - NY receipts, 1952-1953 (Volume 11)
    - NY receipts, 1954-1955 (Volume 12)
    - NY receipts, Aug-Nov 1955 (Volume 13)
  - Estate correspondence
    - Estate correspondence A-E, undated (Volume 14)
    - Estate correspondence F-K, undated (Volume 15)
    - Estate correspondence L-P, undated (Volume 16)
    - Estate correspondence Q-Z, undated (Volume 17)
  - Estate items
    - Estate documents, 1926-1928 (Volume 18)
    - Estate documents, 1924-1928 (Volume 19)
    - Estate mAprs, undated (Volume 20)
    - Estate receipts, 1924 (Volume 21)
    - Estate statements, 1926-1928 (Volume 22)
    - Estate statements, 1928-1929 (Volume 23)
  - Estate documents (George F. Butterworth-Attn.)
    - Estate documents (George F. Butterworth-Attn.), Sep-Nov 1924 (Volume 24)
    - Estate documents (George F. Butterworth-Attn.), Sep-Dec 1924 (Volume 25)
    - Estate documents (George F. Butterworth-Attn.), Jan-Feb 1925 (Volume 26)
    - Estate documents (George F. Butterworth-Attn.), Mar-Apr 1925 (Volume 27)
    - Estate documents (George F. Butterworth-Attn.), Apr 1925 (Volume 28)
    - Estate documents (George F. Butterworth-Attn.), May 1925 (Volume 29)
    - Estate documents (George F. Butterworth-Attn.), Jun 1925 (Volume 30)
    - Estate documents (George F. Butterworth-Attn.), Jul-Aug 1925 (Volume 31)
    - Estate documents (George F. Butterworth-Attn.), Aug-Oct 1925 (Volume 32)
    - Estate documents (George F. Butterworth-Attn.), Nov 1925 (Volume 33)
    - Estate documents (George F. Butterworth-Attn.), Dec 1925-Jan 1926 (Volume 34)
    - Estate documents (George F. Butterworth-Attn.), Jan-Mar 1926 (Volume 35)
    - Estate documents (George F. Butterworth-Attn.), Apr-Jul 1926 (Volume 36)
    - Estate documents (George F. Butterworth-Attn.), Jul 1936-Jan 1937 (Volume 37)
    - Estate documents (George F. Butterworth-Attn.), Feb-Jul 1937 (Volume 38)
    - Estate documents (George F. Butterworth-Attn.), Jun-Sep 1927 (Volume 39)
    - Estate documents (George F. Butterworth-Attn.), Sep-Dec 1927 (Volume 40)
    - Estate documents (George F. Butterworth-Attn.), 1927-1928 (Volume 41)
  - Cadwalader Wickersham & Taft (formerly GFB)
    - Cadwalader Wickersham & Taft (formerly GFB), Apr-Dec 1928 (Volume 42)
    - Estate - CWT, 1928 (Volume 43)
    - CWT, 1930 (Volume 44)
  - Huntington - general correspondence
    This portion of the Archer Milton Huntington Papers inventory (Volumes 45 through 82) has been entirely merged into the Correspondence-subject files for the
    Anna Hyatt Huntington Papers
    (see "Related Material" above). Volumes 45 through 82 no longer exist in this collection.
    - Huntington - general correspondence, 1942-1943 (Volume 45)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, 1943 (Volume 46)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, 1943 (Volume 47)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, 1943 (Volume 48)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, 1944 (Volume 49)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, 1945 (Volume 50)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, 1946 (Volume 51)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, 1947 (Volume 52)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, 1947 (Volume 53)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, 1947 (Volume 54)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, 1947 (Volume 55)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, Jan-Mar 1948 (Volume 56)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, Apr-Jun 1948 (Volume 57)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, Jul-Sep 1948 (Volume 58)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, Jun-Dec 1948 (Volume 59)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, 1948 (Volume 60)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, Jan-May 1949 (Volume 61)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, Jun-Dec 1949 (Volume 62)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, May-Dec 1950 (Volume 63)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, 1952 (Volume 64)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, Mar-May 1954 (Volume 65)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, 1954 (Volume 66)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, May-Jul 1954 (Volume 67)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, Jul-Sep 1954 (Volume 68)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, Nov-Dec 1954 (Volume 69)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, Dec 54-Feb 1955 (Volume 70)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, Mar 1955 (Volume 71)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, Mar-Apr 1955 (Volume 72)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, May-Jun 1955 (Volume 73)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, Jun-Jul 1955 (Volume 74)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, Jul-Aug 1955 (Volume 75)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, Jul-Aug 1955 (Volume 76)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, Sep 1955 (Volume 77)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, Sep 1955 (Volume 78)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, Sep-Oct 1955 (Volume 79)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, Sep-Ost 1955 (Volume 80)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, Oct-Nov 1955 (Volume 81)
    - Huntington - general correspondence, Nov-Dec 1955 (Volume 82)
  - Bank of Central Hanover-receipts
    - Bank of Central Hanover-receipts, Apr-Jun 1946 (Volume 83)
    - Bank of Central Hanover-receipts, 1947 (Volume 84)
    - Bank of Central Hanover-receipts, 1948 (Volume 85)
    - Bank of Central Hanover-receipts, Aug-Dec 1948 (Volume 86)
    - Bank of Central Hanover-receipts, 1949 (Volume 87)
    - Bank of Central Hanover-receipts, Jul 1950-Jun 1951 (Volume 88)
    - Bank of Central Hanover-receipts, 1951-1952 (Volume 89)
    - 90a Bank of Central Hanover-receipts, 1952-1953 (Volume 90a)
    - Bank of Central Hanover-receipts, Nov 1953-Apr 1954 (Volume 90)
    - Bank of Central Hanover-receipts, May-Dec 1954 (Volume 91)
    - Bank of Central Hanover-receipts, Oct 54-Aug 1955 (Volume 92)
    - Bank of Central Hanover-receipts, Aug-Dec 1955 (Volume 93)
  - Bill sent to Hanover Bank
    - Bill sent to Hanover Bank, 1952 (Volume 94)
    - Bill sent to Hanover Bank, 1953 (Volume 95)
    - Bill sent to Hanover Bank, 1954 (Volume 96)
    - Bill sent to Hanover Bank, 1955 (Volume 97)
    - Bill sent to Hanover Bank, 1955 (Volume 98)
  - Payment statements (AMH)
    - Payment statements (AMH), 1943-1947 (Volume 99)
    - Payment statements (AMH), 1947-1948 (Volume 100)
    - Payment statements (AMH), 1948 (Volume 101)
    - Payment statements (AMH), 1949 (Volume 102)
    - Payment statements (AMH), 1949-50 (Volume 103)
    - Payment statements (AMH), 1950 (Volume 104)
    - Payment statements (AMH), 1951 (Volume 105)
    - Payment statements (AMH), 1951-1952 (Volume 106)
    - Payment statements (AMH), 1953 (Volume 107)
    - Payment statements (AMH), 1953 (Volume 108)
    - Payment statements (AMH), 1954 (Volume 109)
    - Payment statements (AMH), 1954 (Volume 110)
    - Payment statements (AMH), Jan-Aug 1955 (Volume 111)
  - Trust Companies
    - Trust Companies (Bankers Union T.), 1951-1955 (Volume 112)
    - Bank of New York & Trust Co., 1925-1926 (Volume 113)
    - Trusts, 1952-1953 (Volume 114)
    - Recent trusts, 1951-1955 (Volume 115)
    - Miscellaneous statements, 1947-1948 (Volume 116)
    - Miscellaneous statements, 1951-1953 (Volume 117)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Misc. banks, 1946 (Volume 118)
    - Misc. banks, 1953 (Volume 119)
    - U.S. Trust Co., undated (Volume 120)
    - U.S. Trust Co., undated (Volume 121)
    - New York Trust Co., 1945-1951 (Volume 122)
    - Daily records, 1943 (Volume 123)
    - Chemical, Haverstraw & South Carolina, 1947-1948 (Volume 124)
    - Cheques (misc.), 1950-1954 (Volume 125)
    - Lawyers Trust Co., 1946-1949 (Volume 126)
    - Guaranty Trust Co. of New York, 1947-1951 (Volume 127)
    - Bankers Trust Co., 1950-1951 (Volume 128)
    - Misc. Q-Z, undated (Volume 129)
    - Taxes, cheques, etc., 1949-1950 (Volume 130)
    - Taxes, banks (Haverstrom), 1952-1953 (Volume 131)
    - Taxes, 1953-1955 (Volume 132)
    - Taxes, 1950-1952 (Volume 133)
    - Hall of Fame, 1955 (Volume 134)
    - J.P. Morgan Co., 1947-1949 (Volume 135)
    - Gifts of land and objects (GI), 1915-1930 (Volume 136)
    - Gifts of land and objects (GI), 1917-1940 (Volume 137)
    - Gifts and endowments, 1948-1952 (Volume 138)
    - Gifts and endowments, 1930s (Volume 139)
    - Transfiles 1 and 2, loose papers